Guide to the Alfred White Van Sinderen Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alfred White Van Sinderen Collection
1782-1969
MS 1095
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(2 boxes)
The collection consists of letters of thirty-five presidents of the United States from George Washington to Lyndon B. Johnson. Each is represented by one letter written in office and one written after leaving office. There are also fifteen other letters either written by a United States president or relating to a United States president.
Van Sinderen, Alfred White, 1924-1998
Conditions Governing Access
All original documents in the collection have been both microfilmed and photocopied due to preservation concerns. Readers must use either the microfilm (HM 104) or photocopies of the collection in box 2.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alfred W. Van Sinderen, 1980-1990.
Existence and Location of Copies
Material originally deposited in 1980 is also available on microfilm (224 frames on 1 reel. 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM104.
Arrangement
The letters are arranged chronologically.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of letters of thirty-five presidents of the United States from George Washington to Lyndon B. Johnson. Each is represented by one letter written in office and one written after leaving office. There are also fifteen other letters either written by a United States president or relating to a United States president. Many of the letters are accompanied by typescripts, notes on historical significance of item, and/or clippings from auction catalogues.
Presidents -- United States; Autographs; Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848; Adams, John, 1735-1826; Arthur, Chester Alan, 1829-1886; Buchanan, James, 1791-1868; Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969; Fillmore, Millard, 1800-1874; Garfield, James A. (James Abram), 1831-1881; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923; Harrison, Benjamin, 1833-1901; Harrison, William Henry, 1773-1841; Hayes, Rutherford B., 1822-1893; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Johnson, Andrew, 1808-1875; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865; Madison, James, 1751-1836; McKinley, William, 1843-1901; Monroe, James, 1758-1831; Pierce, Franklin, 1804-1869; Polk, James K. (James Knox), 1795-1849; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930; Taylor, Zachary, 1784-1850; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972; Tyler, John, 1790-1862; Van Buren, Martin, 1782-1862; Washington, George, 1732-1799
- Originals
  Conditions Governing Access
  All original documents in the collection have been both microfilmed and photocopied due to preservation concerns. Readers must use either the microfilm (HM 104) or photocopies of the collection in box 2.
  - George Washington to James Madison, Jr., Mount Vernon, 1786 November 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - George Washington to James McHenry, Philadelphia, 1798 November 13 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Thomas Jefferson to Sharp Delaney (Written on verso of letter from Delaney, 2 Nov 1792), 1792 November (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Thomas Jefferson to John Page, Rosewell, Va., 1802 April 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - James Madison to [underline], Washington, 1803 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - James Madison to Tench Coxe, Orange City, Va., 1823 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - James Monroe to George Washington, Philadelphia, 1794 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - James Monroe to unnamed government official, Oak Hill, 1819 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - John Quincy Adams to William S. Smith, Stockholm, 1814 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - John Quincy Adams to Asa Gray, Washington, 1846 July 16 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Andrew Jackson to Andrew Jackson, Jr., Philadelphia, 1831 March 29 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Andrew Jackson to Amos Kendall, Hermitage, 1841 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Martin Van Buren to Stephen Van Rensselear, Washington, 1837 February 26 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Martin Van Buren to Caleb Cushing, Washington, 1837 July 29 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - William H. Harrison to Thaddeus Stevens, Cincinnati, 1835 November 28 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - William H. Harrison to John Bell (Secretary of War), Washington, 1841 March 13 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - John Tyler to the House of Representatives, Washington, 1842 February 26 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - John Tyler to J.S. Cunningham, Sherwood Forest, 1852 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - James K. Polk to Lewis Cass, Washington, 1846 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - James K. Polk, Treaty settling the Oregon Boundary, Washington, 1846 June 19 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Zachary Taylor to J.T. Eubank, Fort Harrison, Indiana Territory, 1812 July 25 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Zachary Taylor to Robert Crooke Ward, Monterey, Mexico, 1847 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Millard Fillmore to H.C. Day, Albany, 1848 November 8 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Millard Fillmore to Secretary of War, Washington (Written on verso of letter from the Jackson Monument Committee with A.D.S. by Winfield Scott), 1850 August 14 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Franklin Pierce to R. Jones, Concord, N.H., 1847 March 2 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Franklin Pierce to R. Jones, Concord, N.H., 1847 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - James Buchanan to Ann J. Stephens, Wheatland, 1852 March 23 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - James Buchanan to Lady Clarendon, Washington, 1857 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Abraham Lincoln to P.S. Harrison, Tremont, Illinois, 1849 September 23 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Abraham Lincoln to Winfield Scott, Washington, 1861 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Andrew Johnson to William M. Lowery, Washington City, 1844 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Andrew Johnson to J. Netherland, Greenville, Tenn, 1872 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Ulysses S. Grant to Maj. Gen. Meade, City Point, 1864 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Ulysses S. Grant to Edwards Pierpont, Washington, 1877 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Rutherford B. Hayes to W.W. Story, Washington, 1877 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Rutherford B. Hayes to Richard Karnis, Fremont, Ohio, 1884 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - James A. Garfield to S.S. Cox, Mentor, Ohio, 1881 January 21 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - James A. Garfield to Lewis Wallace, Washington, 1881 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Chester A. Arthur to Edwards Pierpont, Washington, 1882 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Chester A. Arthur to Park Godwin, Washington, 1885 March 7 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Grover Cleveland to Daniel Dougherty, Washington, 1887 April 12 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Grover Cleveland to Master George Tampers, New York, 1890 November 10 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Benjamin Harrison to Charles Elmer Rice, Washington, 1891 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Benjamin Harrison to May (daughter-in-law), Indianapolis, 1893 July 3 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - William McKinley to Jesse Weick, Canton, Ohio, 1896 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - William McKinley to Paul Dana, Washington, 1898 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Theodore Roosevelt to Mr. Chapman, Washington, 1889 October 8 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Theodore Roosevelt to George A. Dyer, New York, 1917 November 6 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - William H. Taft to Vespasian Warner, Washington, 1905 April 14 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - William H. Taft to Charles Joline, Washington, 1910 December 28 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Woodrow Wilson to James Gayley, Princeton, 1900 January 10 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Woodrow Wilson to Edward A. Filene, Washington, 1918 August 22 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Warren G. Harding to Van [underline], Washington, 1918 July 17 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Warren G. Harding to John Barton Payne, Washington, 1922 August 16 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Calvin Coolidge to Father O'Connell, Boston, 1920 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Calvin Coolidge to Herman Hegedorn, Washington, 1925 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Herbert C. Hoover to Mr. Pierce, 1934 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Herbert C. Hoover to John M. Morehead, New York, 1961 August 12 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Franklin D. Roosevelt to Mr. Pierce, Washington, 1935 March 17 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Franklin D. Roosevelt to Alben W. Barkley, Washington, 1940 July 31 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Harry S. Truman to George Seldes, Washington (with copy of letter to H.S.T. from Seldes, 1944 Aug 8), 1944 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Harry S. Truman to Frank M. Swacker, Washington, 1947 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Dwight D. Eisenhower to Mrs. George V.H. Mosely, Washington (with copy of T.L.S., Patrick Hurley to George Van Horn Mosely), 1933 April (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Dwight D. Eisenhower to Alden S. Condict, (1952) August 26 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - John F. Kennedy to Howard E. Marston, Hyannis, Mass., (1954 September 2) (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - John F. Kennedy to Mrs. R. Warfield, Washington, 1960 August 30 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Lyndon B. Johnson to Zilmon J. Boothe, Jr., Washington, 1956 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Lyndon B. Johnson to Basil O'Connor, Austin, Texas, 1969 February 25 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Adams, John Quincy to Thomas B. Adams, 1801 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Harrison, William Henry to Thomas Jesup, 1824 June 18 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Buchanan, James to Andrew Jackson, 1836 June 4 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Taylor, Zachary to Henry Carey, 1849 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Fillmore, Millard to Mrs. Kellogg, 1856 September 16 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Garfield, James A. to Wallace Ford, 1857 November 26 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Arthur, Chester A. to William Arthur, 1858 March 23 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Pierce, Franklin to Mrs. Alfred Aiken, 1869 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore to Felix Frankfurter, 1911 December 13 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Coolidge, Calvin to Mr. Greenly, 1932 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Hoover, Herbert: press statement, 1935 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin: TLS to Franklin Roosevelt from James Forrestal, 1942 Feb 4, countersigned by Roosevelt, 1942 February 6 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Kennedy, Jacqueline Bouvier to Mrs. Secrest, [1959?] September 3 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor to Mr. Mandell, 1960 January 19 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Perry, Malcolm O.: ALS to "Dear Marshall" concerning the death of John F. Kennedy, 1963 December 18 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - John Adams to Benjamin Rush, the Hague, 1782 Apr 22 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John Adams to James Brackett, Quincey, Massachusetts, 1819 Feb 10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Photocopies (Box 2)